I wanted to speak about uh the issue of
the hindrance of sloth and to tina mida
is the pie.
>> Mhm.
>> So I just I like to call it just
laziness. M
>> and in the sutras
um there's a simile for this kind of
state and the Buddha says suppose there is a
and the Buddha says suppose there is a
bowl of water covered with water plants
and algae a man with good eyesight
standing on the bank would not see his
own facial reflection as it really is.
So too, when a monk dwells with a mind
overcome by sloth and torper, he does
not understand what is for his own
welfare, for the welfare of others or
for for the welfare of both.
>> So it's a it's a covering.
It makes things unclear. If your mind is
clouded, indolent, lazy,
um no perspective is because you made it
so directly
even more so than uh if you were say you
know have a tendency towards desire too
much or tendency towards ill will. Yeah,
that's also result of your actions but
it kind of gets its own momentum.
Um but with this like the momentum is
always directly uh um sustained the
momentum of your indolence if you could
even call it a momentum through you
choosing to uh to not go against it to
not really just uh like um pull yourself
out of it. That's why it's always
practically manifested through yeah
choosing out of a preference to say not
think about certain things because oh
they're a bit uncomfortable or I can't
deal with that now or I'll address that
later procrastinate.
uh you could get up when you wake up.
Oh, that's just that would be a bit
uncomfortable. So, I should rather just
uh indulge in this completely
unnecessary slimy, sticky, heavy uh comfort that I'm
slimy, sticky, heavy uh comfort that I'm
currently in. Uh so, it's always by that
immediate choice. That's how you you're
you're maintaining that very kind of um
sticky way weighty uh
state of mind that then it feels like,
oh, I can't break out of this, but you
can. and you just get up and go for a
long walk, you're just going to feel you
have no motivation to do it. You have no
no reason to do it. You're sleepy. You
want to rest. Just know I'll just go out
and walk.
Um it's kind of in a way it's that
simple. But it would go against the
entire grain of your mind there and
then. Yeah. You just there's
Yeah. You just there's
you're trying to just Yeah. stay with
comfort. You don't want to
>> Yeah. Yeah. Well, it's not even and and
and again like see it can go that far.
You know, if you're reaching like the
the levels of of like chronic depression
and so on, you're not even staying with
the comfort.
>> It's uncomfortable already. It's
uncomfortable. >> But the thought of [clears throat]
>> But the thought of [clears throat]
kind of moving or at least exerting some
going against some degree of inertia
feels even worse.
So because what you're currently in is
less uncomfortable than the projected
idea of going against this inertia,
that's why I'll just stay with it. But
it's it's uncomfortable. It's not it's
it's far from being agreeable and
pleasant at that point. So if you know
one is laying around
uh after after you've genu you have a
rest >> and uh you wake up you want to and
>> and uh you wake up you want to and
there's a tendency to h just stay in
bed. I just can't stay here a little bit
longer and let just go with the mind's
thoughts here and there
>> and
but then then okay I'm just get up go
for a walk as you say but uh
is that not now just kind of reaction
like a the wrong thing to do rather than
well no it's a reaction to the right
extent. So if things are too loose, you need to
So if things are too loose, you need to
react towards tightening.
Not for its own sake, but for the sake
of tightening that which was too loose.
But like if I just try to stay in bed
[laughter] and just say, "Well, now I'm
just going to just be awake." You're
not, you know, it's already like if you
try to stay in bed because you don't
really want to stay in bed or you're not
that pressured to stay in bed, but for
whatever reason, you choose to stay in
bed. Yeah. But if you're clearly staying
in bed because getting out of the bed,
>> the inertia that that kind of exhibits
is just h I don't want to bother with
that now. Then whatever you do on
account of staying in bed will be done
on account of already made compromise.
So that's the point like it's not about
oh I will start restricting my sleep and
set up the alarm to wake me up in the
middle of the night and then I must
force myself. It's like no it's when
that choice presents itself
>> right
>> to either go with the inertia
path of less resistance
um or go against it. What do you choose?
And that choice will present you don't
have to manufacture it or force it.
you're going to have ample opportunity
to exercise the right choice when it
comes to the hindrances uh just on
account of basic restraint and the
precepts. So you don't need to go to the
extremes and start as I said tormenting
or depriving yourself of sleep to get to
this point. It's already there these
little as I said little paths of of less
resistance here and when you know when
you're aware what do you choose that's
what matters. So like after a hard day's
work or working hard in whatever on some
project and you generally are tired
and you generally are tired
then there's a choice maybe at the end
of the day you get back and you rest I
just want to zone out you know I want to
just kind of
>> uh drift into
nonsense you know even just watching
things on the internet just drift away
and kind of forget about
>> yeah That's kind of that's going with
the laziness. That's going with the the
hinges basically.
>> Well, yeah. You need to see where the
where the line between factual need of
rest and indolence is crossed. Where
that line is crossed. So when you come
back from like if you're genuinely
tired, which obviously you would be
sooner or later.
>> Yeah. One thing is to then have the rest
that you actually need and another thing
is to turn that rest into exactly like
uh mindless uh completely like loss of
context, loss of perspective uh
entertainment, indulgence
indulgence
>> which obviously for people is kind of
became synonymous with rest. In other
words, >> even if they come home and start resting
>> even if they come home and start resting
like factually resting, unless they
enter into the that as I said half
asleep state of entertainment and
laziness they won't feel like they
rested but all the factually no you have
rested like resting means just sitting
down calming down
>> not working not not not distracting
yourself either but the distraction has
become synonymous with rest so that
needs to be unlearned.
So initially when you don't give into
distraction it will feel like you
haven't rested but that's not so you are
actually having you you have rested but
just your mind hasn't got what it wants
so it's going to feel a bit restless on
account of that
but it's a different thing to have a
restless mind and to factually need
actually just to rest because you were
tired. So there's you can sit down and relax
So there's you can sit down and relax
physically. You are actually getting
rest, not doing anything.
>> Go to sleep, rest,
>> not letting not even watching things. So
your eyes are at rest as well. Yeah.
>> Just everything's at rest,
>> but your mind is not.
>> Yeah. So you have to unlearn the the the
the um the identification, the
gratuitous identification of the factual
rest with entertainment and
mindlessness. When you let your mind disappear in the
When you let your mind disappear in the
content or whatever, that's not resting.
>> Yeah. So, how do you get the mind?
>> Well, by saying no to the extent of
entertainment and mindless
>> mindless wandering and distraction and
indolence >> and then it starts going.
>> and then it starts going.
>> So, saying no to those things. So, you
need to rest, go lay down. Oh, while
you're laying down, you want to watch
something, listen something. Well, say
no to that.
>> Oh, but that will disturb the mind. Yes,
the mind might be disturbed initially
until it unlearns the bad habits,
>> but you are getting the rest that you
physically need. So, you have to kind of
go through a certain amount of
withdrawal from that dependence on those
uh
>> mindless activities.
>> Yeah. The mind's already disturbed.
So, and then you saying no to its uh
need for entertain entertainment.
It's still agitated but eventually it
realizes >> Yeah, it's agitated but it's not uh it
>> Yeah, it's agitated but it's not uh it
won't be tired.
>> Yeah.
>> Like
initially, as I said, distraction is the
only way to get rid of tiredness
because it implies some degree of
factual resting. But my point is that
factual resting does not require you to
go as far as the distraction.
>> Yeah.
>> So that's what person needs to discern
through through practice. You can you
can theorize and ponder about it all you
want. But the fact is basically you
actually have to start doing it. You
have to start going against that that
inertia when present itself enduring it
not acting out of it on on those levels
of of conscious choices when they're
clearly outlined there. when you know
what you're choosing, when you know what
you're doing.
>> And I [clears throat] was thinking that
another relaxation should result in
feeling rested at the end of it. So if
you're doing something as a relaxation
and you're feeling even more worse, more
tired, >> that work
>> that work
>> your sensuality though that's used as a
relaxation technique,
>> you don't feel rested and light after
it. Burden free. You know,
>> the weight has been lifted. Now it's
even worse.
>> Yeah,
definitely.